We start, today's דף daf is כ"ז, Chaf Zayin, and we begin
from the actually the top of כ"ז עמוד א', Chaf Zayin Amud
Aleph, we're a little bit ahead. So let's take a look. So
we have been discussing the issue about which type of fabrics, specifically
about linen, about flax, I'm sorry, about flax and wool, and whether
those make fabrics in order to become טמא. tamei. And the גמרא
Gemara quoted yesterday on רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rav Shimon ben Elazar
that said that anything that comes from a tree that is not
flax, considering flax as a plant as coming from a tree, we'll
discuss that later,
cannot become טמא. tamei. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael saying that anything
that is not wool and linen cannot become טמא. tamei. And the
גמרא Gemara assumes that the first statement was not limiting itself to
things that come from a tree, it really meant to exclude anything
that's not wool and linen, and essentially they're the same position. The
only debate is whether רב שמעון בן אלעזר, Rav Shimon ben Elazar,
the first position, would allow, would say that if it was another
type of a fabric, whether it would become טמא tamei if it
were bigger than three by three fingers, if it was three by
three טפחים, tefachim, would that make a difference? Maybe then larger sizes
would be significant with these other fabrics. So the גמרא Gemara now
continues the following, that was a debate of אביי ורבא. Abaye ve-Rava.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, it's about ten lines down on כ"ז עמוד
א' Chaf Zayin Amud Aleph by the asterisk. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
said Abaye, האי תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, hai Tanna de-bei Rabbi Yishmael,
that תנא Tanna from the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, מפיק
מאידך תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, mafik mi-idach Tanna de-bei Rabbi Yishmael, is
sort
of excludes, rejects, is a contradiction to the other תנא Tanna from
the house of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So there are two ברייתות
baraitot from the ישיבה Yeshiva of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael which actually
teach contradictory things. The one we taught yesterday says that anything that's
not wool and linen is not a fabric that can become טמא.
tamei. And here's the one we're going to teach today. דתני דבי
רבי ישמעאל, De-tani de-bei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught in the house of
רבי ישמעאל: Rabbi Yishmael:
בגד
אין לי אלא בגד. beged ein li ella beged. It says בפרשת
נגעים, be-parashat Nega'im, so this is again from נגעים, Nega'im, from צרעת,
Tzara'at, from the spot. So it says if you have a garment,
בגד צמר או בבגד פשתים. beged tzemer o be-veged pishtim. I only
know wool and linen, that those are fabrics that can become טמא.
tamei. מניין לרבות צמר גמלים וצמר ארנבים? Minayin lerabot tzemer gemalim ve-tzemer
anavim? How do I know about wool that's not classic wool, that's
not wool from sheep, lamb's wool? How do I know wool that's
really rabbit, that's from camels or rabbit fur? נוצה של עזים, Notza
shel izim, or the hair or like the down of goats? Apparently
there would be, you know, they both use goat hair and some
type of a downy material from the goats. והשירים והכלך והסריקין, ve-hashirim
ve-haklach ve-haserikin, and all these different types of silks? How do I
know that these as well can become a fabric that can become
טמא? tamei? So notice we're not only including things that are non-classic
wools, but we're actually
including even things that have nothing to do with wool, like various
types of silk. So how do I know those can become טמא?
tamei? תלמוד לומר או בגד, Talmud lomar o veged, or a garment.
So the או o is coming to include other types of material.
So this is what we quote an excerpt of yesterday. Yesterday we
quoted it to support the reading of רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rav
Shimon ben Elazar that he says that other garments can become other
fabrics can become טמא tamei if they're big enough. Here we see
that it's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael himself who says that. And yesterday
it seemed like everybody agreed that according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
other fabrics were completely out. So how do you, so this is
a contradictory ברייתא. baraita. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael seems to be contradicting
himself. So what do you do with it? רבא אמר, Rava amar,
כי לית ליה להאי תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל בשאר בגדים בשאר בגדים
שלש על
שלש. Ki leit lei le-hai Tanna de-bei Rabbi Yishmael bi-sh'ar begadim bi-sh'ar
begadim shalosh al shalosh. When does, you're right, yesterday רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael said that the things that are not wool or linen don't
become טמא, tamei, but that was only talking about small swaths, three
by three fingers. שלש על שלש אית ליה, Shalosh al shalosh it
lei, a big, a big section, three by three טפחים, tefachim, like
nine inches by nine inches, there רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say.
So basically what we're saying is the exact same distinction רבא Rava
said yesterday for רב שמעון בן אלעזר. Rav Shimon ben Elazar. Other
fabrics, can they become טמא? tamei? Yes, if they're big enough. Small
little swath of three by three fingers, no. Three inches by three
inches, no. But a big piece of three by three טפחים, tefachim,
like nine inches or a foot by a foot, that yes, that
can become טמא tamei even of other fabrics. That is what yesterday
we said that that's what רב שמעון בן אלעזר Rav Shimon ben
Elazar is saying. Here we're saying that's to reconcile this contradiction of
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, where in one ברייתא baraita he says no
other fabrics and in another ברייתא baraita he says yes other fabrics.
So that seems like a very simple, straightforward resolution. We have though
a problem, the גמרא Gemara says. והא רבא הוא דאמר שלש על
שלש בשאר בגדים לרבי שמעון בן אלעזר אית ליה לתנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל לית ליה. Ve-ha Rava hu de-amar shalosh al shalosh bi-sh'ar begadim
le-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar it lei le-Tanna de-bei Rabbi Yishmael leit lei.
That is a great distinction. The only problem is that yesterday רבא
Rava *Rava* said that that was true for רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar*, he holds a distinction
of other garments other fabrics between three fingers versus three טפחים tefachim
*tefachim*, but he said that רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* completely
rejected it. רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael* said other fabrics were
completely out. So how here can you use that distinction to reconcile
this contradiction of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael*, if yesterday you
said that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael, *Rabbi Yishmael* was categorical, across the
board, these other fabrics were out? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
הדר ביה רבא Rava מההוא *hadar bei Rava me-ha-hu*. Okay, רבא Rava,
*Rava* reversed himself. Yesterday, you see how things change from a day.
Yesterday, רבא Rava *Rava* said that that was debated, but today he's
confronted with this contradiction, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* in one
place seems to say other fabrics yes, in another place other fabrics
no. So today רבא Rava *Rava* is saying, you know what, what
I said yesterday about רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
*Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* that size matters, here too, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* would also agree that size matters, you know what,
and there's no debate between רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*.
So אביי Abaye. *Abaye* was right all along that they say the
same thing, but not like אביי Abaye *Abaye*, אביי Abaye. *Abaye* said
that they both categorically reject other fabrics. I say they both make
a distinction between a small swath, three by three fingers, that only
by wool and linen, other fabrics no, a big thing, three by
three טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*, that they agree other fabrics yes. Okay, so
exactly what רבא Rava *Rava* said yesterday that other fabrics will become
טמא tamei, *tamei* if they are large enough, here he is saying
that that is actually agreed upon, that's not just רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar*, that is agreed
upon, רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* says the same thing,
and that resolves the contradiction from both, what do you call it,
from the two statements of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*. Okay, that seems
like a very nice answer. Just have to say that he, you
know, took a step back from what he said yesterday. ואיבעית אימא
*Ve'iba'it eima*, or here's another possibility, הא רב פפא אמרה *ha Rav
Papa amrah*. This last statement, it's always a question which one, but
let's say the last statement רב פפא *Rav Papa* said. Now why
would they assign a statement of רבא Rava? *Rava* to רב פפא
*Rav Papa*? Because רב פפא *Rav Papa* was רבא Rava. *Rava*'s תלמיד
מובהק *talmid muvhak*, he was his primary student and he took over
the ישיבה *yeshiva* after רבא Rava *Rava* died, and therefore many times
רב פפא *Rav Papa* would say something and people just assume oh,
of course that's a רבא Rava *Rava* statement, he's getting it from
רבא Rava *Rava*. But actually originally it was not a רבא Rava
*Rava* statement, it was a רב פפא *Rav Papa* statement. So, one
of these statements was said by רב פפא *Rav Papa*. Let's assume
this last one. So this last statement to reconcile, רבא *Rava* himself
held that this is a debate. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* thinks that other fabrics yes if
they're big enough, רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* says other fabrics never. But
רב פפא *Rav Papa*, in order to reconcile these two statements of
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* that seem to contradict, רב פפא *Rav Papa*
said even רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* is on board with this distinction.
Even רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* says that if other fabrics are big
enough that they will become טמא tamei? *tamei*. Okay, so now what
we've got is a statement of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* that says
other fabrics yes and we can reconcile it by saying that if
they're big enough even רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* will agree, and that
is different from what רבא *Rava* said yesterday, either רבא *Rava* reversed
himself or at least רב פפא *Rav Papa* is saying this. Now
again, as I said, this is relevant not only for laws of
טומאה וטהרה Tumah v’Taharah. *tum'ah ve-taharah*, it's relevant for things like what
garments are obligated in ציצית tzitzis. *tzitzit*. Are we gonna say, right
now at least according to one approach, everybody, both רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* and רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael*, both agree that if the fabric is large enough, it's
you know it's at least like nine inches by nine inches, then
even other fabrics are considered a garment, can become טמא tamei. *tamei*,
and presumably same answer when it comes to ציצית tzitzis. *tzitzit*. So
let's take a view now, let's continue going in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, רב פפא אמר *Rav
Papa amar*, now רב פפא *Rav Papa* says, some people say דרב
פפא אמר *de-Rav Papa amar*, but this seems like that was a
previous statement by רבא *Rava*. Maybe we're going to attribute it to
רב פפא *Rav Papa*, who knows, that was a statement of רבא
*Rava* that says that רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* agrees by large sizes.
רב פפא *Rav Papa* himself clearly in his own name has another
approach. רב פפא אמר אף כל לאתויי כלאים *Rav Papa amar af
kol le-atoyei kilayim*. Yesterday we said, everything goes by wool and linen.
Okay, now what we assumed that meant was that for טומאה tumah.
*tum'ah*, according to רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*, only wool and linen, other
fabrics no. But again, we see today that רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*
includes other fabrics for טומאה tumah *tum'ah*. So way to reconcile it
number one is the size of the cloth matters. Here comes רב
פפא *Rav Papa* and saying way to reconcile it number two. That
really other fabrics yes, can become טמא tamei, *tamei*, that's what we
said today. When did רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* say yesterday only wool
and linen? Not to say small sizes, that wasn't the point. Only
wool and linen was to say when it comes to the איסור
*issur* of שעטנז *shatnez*. When it comes to כלאים *kilayim*, that's only
wool and linen. So you know what, for טומאה tumah *tum'ah* you're
right, other fabrics yes, all he was saying yesterday when he emphasized
wool and linen was to say a law about שעטנז *shatnez*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, כלאים *kilayim*, שעטנז *shatnez*? בהדיא כתיב בהו
*behedya ketiv behu*, it's explicit in a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Who needs
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* to tell me that? לא תלבש שעטנז *lo
tilbash shatnez*, do not wear שעטנז *shatnez*, צמר ופשתים יחדו *tzemer u-pishtim
yachdav*, wool and linen together. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka daitach amina*, I would have thought הני מילי
דרך לבישה *hanei milei derech levisha*. That says לא תלבש *lo tilbash*.
The תורה Torah. *Torah* says twice not to wear שעטנז *shatnez*. One
is this פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*, לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו *lo
tilbash shatnez tzemer ufishtim yachdav*, don't wear it where it mentions wool
and linen,
and the other is ובגד ubeged כלאים שעטנז לא יעלה עליך *ubeged
kilayim shatnez lo yaaleh alecha*, and a garment of כלאים *kilayim*, שעטנז
*shatnez* you should not put on you. From there we learn that
it's prohibited not just to wear שעטנז *shatnez*, but even to put
it upon you like let's say to have a שעטנז *shatnez* blanket.
Now in that second פסוק pasuk *pasuk* it did not mention wool
and linen. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to say that's
why I need רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka daitach
amina*, I would have thought to say הני מילי דרך לבישה *hanei
milei derech levisha*, that when is שעטנז *shatnez* forbidden, when do we
know that שעטנז *shatnez* is wool and linen, that's if you're wearing
it. אבל בהעלאה *aval behaala*, if you're not wearing it, the other
פסוק *pasuk* ובגד כלאים שעטנז לא יעלה עליך *ubeged kilayim shatnez lo
yaaleh alecha*, it's just going on you, it's like a blanket. Maybe
I would say כל תרי מיני אסור *kol terei minei assur*, it
doesn't say wool and linen in that verse. So maybe everything is
forbidden, even any two separate types of fabrics woven together. So therefore
I needed רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* to tell me it's always defined
as wool and linen, not only when you wear it, even when
you cover yourself with it, even like a blanket. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, who needs רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* for
that? ולאו קל וחומר kal vachomer הוא *velao kavachomer hu*? Isn't it
a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kavachomer*? ומה לבישה דקא מתהני כולי גופיה
מכלאים *uma levisha dika misheni kulei gufei mikilayim*, when you wear it
your whole body is benefiting from the כלאים *kilayim*, so wearing is
the most extreme form, ואמרת צמר ופשתים יחדיו לא *veamart tzemer ufishtim
yachdav lo*, you're only going to define it by wool and linen,
not by other things. העלאה *haala*, when it's just on top of
you and you're not wearing it, לא כל שכן *lo kol shekein*,
how much more so should I of course limit it to wool
and linen. So if the wool and linen is by wearing, certainly
it's only wool and linen by this other form which is a
weaker form. You could even go further. It's not just the other
form is weaker, that wearing includes העלאה *haala*, includes putting it on
top of you, and even there it's only wool and linen. So
clearly it's always defined as wool and linen, you don't need a
verse to teach me that שעטנז *shatnez* is wool and linen, it's
an explicit verse. אלא דרב פפא בדיחותא היא *ella derav pappa bedusa
hi*. Okay, what רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said is a בדיחותא היא
*bedusa hi*. It's a question of what בדיחותא היא *bedusa hi* means,
means it's a joke, means it's nonsense. But anyway that's a way
of sort of dismissing it. You know clearly that was sort of
like a non-thought through statement. Okay, it is true that שעטנז *shatnez*
is only wool and linen, but you don't need רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi
Ishmael* to teach me that. So now we have two answers. Does
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* say other garments can become טמא tamei. *tamei*?
Yesterday he seemed to say no, only wool and linen, today yes.
Answer number one is only wool and linen for small sizes, other
fabrics for large sizes. Answer number two is only wool and linen
for שעטנז *shatnez*, other fabrics for becoming טמא tamei, *tamei*. The problem
is we didn't need רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* to tell me that.
So now we're going to give answer number three. רב נחמן Rav
Nachman בר יצחק אמר אף כל לאתויי *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar
af kol laasuyei* top of כ''ז ע''ב *chaf zayin amud beis*, everything
when it says everything else is only wool and linen. What does
that mean that other things are wool and linen? לאתויי ציצית tzitzis
*laasuyei tzitzis*. That the garment that's obligated in ציצית tzitzis *tzitzis*, what
I've been giving you all along as a good practical application, that's
what רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* is saying. He says look guys, when
it comes to טומאה tumah, *tumah*, that's the ברייתא Braitah *braisa* we
said today, other fabrics can become טמא tamei *tamei*. When it comes
to garments that are obligated in ציצית tzitzis, *tzitzis*, that's a more
narrow category. That's only wool and linen. So even if I agree
that other fabrics טומאה tumah? *tumah* yes, what we said today, but
what we learn from נגעים nega'im, *negaim*, what we learn from צרעת
tzara'at, *tzaraas* where the תורה Torah, *Torah* emphasizes wool and linen is
not טומאה tum'ah *tumah* which you would think we would learn. No,
that's other fabrics, but what we learn from צרעת tzara'at *tzaraas* is
wool and linen only are obligated in ציצית tzitzis *tzitzis*, only those
garments. So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says.
ציצית tzitzis? *tzitzis*? You're talking about ציצית tzitzis? *tzitzis*? בהדיא כתיב *behedaya
ksiv*, it says explicitly לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים *lo tilbash shatnez
tzemer ufishtim*. Do not wear שעטנז *shatnez* wool and linen like we
just said before and וכתיב *uksiv* and the immediately next verse is
גדילים תעשה לך *gedilim taaseh lach*, make for yourself ציצית tzitzis, *tzitzis*.
So by that juxtaposition, we say that ציצית tzitzis. *tzitzis* are on
wool and linen garments only, wool or linen, not wool and linen.
Okay, so we know from the פסוק *pasuk* that ציצית tzitzis, *tzitzis*
are only wool and linen garments and therefore we do not need
to learn it from רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*. So it's quite interesting.
Here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* takes it for granted that the מצוה
mitzvah. *mitzvah* of ציצית tzitzis *tzitzis* is limited to wool and linen
garments even if when for טומאה tum'ah, *tumah* purposes a garment is
defined as other fabrics as well. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
לא סלקא דעתך אמינא כדרבא *lo salka daitach amina kiderava*. It's not
so explicit. I might have thought that other garments are obligated in
ציצית tzitzis, *tzitzis* like רבא *Rava* says. דרבא רמי *DeRava rami*, רבא
*Rava* showed a contradiction. כתיב הכנף מן כנף min kenaph. *ksiv hakanaf
minkanaf*, it says you should put on ציצית tzitzis, הכנף *tzitzis hakanaf*
on the corner פתיל תכלת *psil techeiles*, a blue string. So why
did it have to say the ציצית tzitzis *tzitzis* of the corner?
We already said you put ציצית tzitzis, *tzitzis* on the corner. So
רבא *Rava* understands. So what that's telling me is is that the
ציצית tzitzis can be made from the same fabric as the corner.
So whatever garment the fabric of the garment is, if it's a
silk garment, you can have silk ציצית. tzitzis If it's a cotton
garment, you can have cotton ציצית. tzitzis That's what we learn from
מן כנף. kanaph, It can be from the same fabric. Okay, so
that's one verse. But then it says, וכתיב צמר ופשתים יחדו. ukesiv
tzemer upishtim yachdav. It juxtaposes ציצית tzitzis to wool and linen to
tell you that the ציצית tzitzis, strings have to be wool or
have to be linen. So the key here is that רבא is
saying the verse about wool and linen is not referring to the
garment, it's referring to the strings. So רבא is saying, assuming that
any type of a garment is obligated in ציצית, tzitzis, and now
he's got a פסוק problem. What fabric, what material do you make
the ציצית tzitzis. from? One verse for רבא, כנף, seems to tell
him you make it from the fabric of the garment, so it
could be any fabric: silk, cotton, whatever. Another verse, wool and linen,
seems to tell him the strings can only be wool or linen.
So what's the הלכה? halacha? What fabric do the strings have to
be? But רבא takes it for granted that the garment can be
of any fabric. So how does רבא reconcile this contradiction? So he
says the following: צמר ופשתים פוטרין בין במינן בין שלא במינן. tzemer
upishtim potrin bein beminan bein shelo beminan. Wool and linen exempt the
garment whether the garment is made of the same type or different.
If you have a wool string on a silk, on cotton, on
polyester, I'll assume artificial fabrics are included that everybody might agree is
not good, but anyway, if you have a wool string on any
of those or if you have a linen string on any of
those, you're fine. Wool and linen strings are always good. However, שאר
מינים, shear minim, other fabrics that are not wool and linen, silk,
cotton, and so on, במינם פוטרין שלא במינם אינם פוטרין, be-minam potrin
shelo be-minam einam potrin, only exempt the garment or only are valid
if they're used with the same type of garment. So can I
use silk ציצית? tzitzis. Yes, if your garment is silk. Can I
use cotton ציצית? tzitzis? Yes, if your garment is cotton. Wool and
linen ציצית, tzitzis, however, or linen you can use on any type
of a garment. That's what רבא learns, that it's talking about the
strings and it's telling you that wool and linen are like the
universal donor. What is that, O-negative or something? They can be used
for anything, whereas the other strings can only be used when they
match the type. What do you see from רבא? That the garment
itself does not have to be wool or linen. It can be
any type of a garment. So now the גמרא Gemara. is saying
it's far from a decided issue what garments are obligated in ציצית.
tzitzis, So when רבי ישמעאל said yesterday only wool and linen garments,
he did not mean for טומאה. tum'ah For טומאה Tumah we see
today other garments are also included. But for ציצית, tzitzis there he's
telling me only wool and linen garments, not like רבא. So the
גמרא Gemara says קמשמע לן, ka mashma lan, that's what he is
telling me. Okay, and with that we end at least resolving this
contradiction of רבי ישמעאל. Now because this is a very practical הלכה
halachic issue, נו, nu, how do we rule? Are other garments obligated
in ציצית tzitzis, or not? So take a look at תוספות. Tosafos.
He says, סלקא דעתך אמינא כדדייקא דרבא. salka dachitach amina kideyaka de-Rava.
You see the תוספות, Tosafos, it's the second new תוספות Tosafos on
the page. At the bottom, he says like this. He says, ונראה
אף על גב דבפרק התכלת אמר רב נחמן השיראים פטורין מן הציצית.
venireh aph al gav
de-be-perek ha-techeiles amar Rav Nachman ha-shirayim peturin min ha-tzitzis.
Even though in מנחות Menachos where we talk about ציצית, tzitzis רב
נחמן says that silk garments are exempt from ציצית, tzitzis; קיימא לן
כרבא דבתראי הוא. kaima lan ke-Rava de-basrai hu. We hold like רבא
who is the like later generation, וחיוב בציצית מדאורייתא. ve-chiyuv be-tzitzis mide-oraisa.
And we say that other garments are obligated in ציצית tzitzis biblically,
cotton garments and so on. So this is a major debate of
ראשונים Rishonim and אחרונים, Acharonim, how do we פסקן pasken about non-wool
and non-linen garments? Are they biblically obligated or not? And it's debated
up through today. So when people are מקפיד makpid to have a
wool ציצית, tzitzis it's because they are trying to be sure they're
יוצא yotzei the מצוה דאורייתא. mitzvah de-oraisa. It's pretty much agreed that
the other garments are obligated דרבנן derabbanan and you can make a
ברכה beracha on it, but nevertheless, if you want to be יוצא
yotzei the דאורייתא, de-oraisa, look, biblically speaking, we don't have to put
on ציצית tzitzis altogether. It's if you're wearing the garment, then you
put ציצית tzitzit. on it. So the whole reason we go out
of our way to put on the garment is because we say
let's use an opportunity to do a מצוה. mitzvah, So the thinking
is might as well make sure that if we're doing a מצוה,
mitzvah, that it's doing a biblical מצוה, mitzvah, not just דרבנן derabbanan
מצוה, mitzvah. and that's why people some people want to make sure
to have wool because of a debate about how we rule. Of
course, you know, sometimes it can be a חומרא chumra that leads
to a קולא kula because sometimes, what do you call it, if
it's the summer and it's hot, if you were wearing cotton ציצית
tzitzit. you'd leave them on, if you're wearing wool ציצית tzitzit you'd
take them off. So fine, so have two pairs of ציצית, wool
and cotton, and wear the cotton ones if the wool ones are
too hot. But at least when you're wearing the wool ones, you're
doing the biblical מצוה. mitzvah Now if you're wearing a טלית. tallis.
טלית גדול tallis gadol and that's made out of wool, then you're
doing a biblical מצוה mitzvah, each day with that, but at least
if you wear for your טלית קטן tallis katan if you want
to be doing it throughout the day, that is the debate: do
we rule wool or do we rule other garments as well, debated
even in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. I should end by saying
that רב משה Rav Moshe has a תשובה teshuvah I mentioned before
polyester, רב משה Rav Moshe has a תשובה teshuvah about man-made fabrics,
polyester, which is basically oil-based, it's completely non-natural,
and רב משה Rav Moshe says that that's not even rabbinically obligated
and רב משה Rav Moshe says you cannot make a ברכה bracha
on polyester ציצית, although I think they do still sell them and
some people still use them and make a ברכה. bracha. Okay, so
that is the question about ציצית. Okay, now we are continuing, that
resolved one of the ways of resolving the contradiction of רבי ישמעאל.
Now the ברייתא Braitah, continues the following way.
אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, Amar Rav Acha brei deRava
leRav Ashi, so רב אחא Rav Acha the son of רבא said
to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, לתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל מאי שנא לענין
טומאה דמרבי שאר בגדים דכתיב או בגד הכא נמי לימא לרבות שאר
בגדים מאשר תכסה בה? letana debei Rabbi Yishmael mai shna leinyan tumah
demarbei shear begadim dechsiv o beged hacha nami leima lerabos shear begadim
measher techaseh ba? So he says, wait a minute, I'm not done
with ציצית. If the reason רבי ישמעאל, the רבי ישמעאל of today,
included other fabrics was because it says או בגד o beged to
include other fabrics that can become
טמא, tamei, so why not include other fabrics for ציצית? It says
אשר תכסה בה, asher techaseh ba, a garment you cover yourself with,
that seems a little bit superfluous. So that is coming to maybe
say anything you cover yourself with, even other fabrics. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, ההיא לאתויי כסות סומא הוא דאתא. Hahi leasuyei ksut
suma hu deata. That's not coming to include other fabrics for ציצית,
that's coming to include people that are obligated in ציצית, even a
סומא, suma, a blind person who wears a garment, you have to
put ציצית on the garment. Why would I have thought otherwise? דתניא,
Datanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita. וראיתם אותו, urisem oso, you
shall see them, the ציצית, and remember the מצוות, mitzvos, פרט לכסות
לילה, prat leksut lailah, from this we exclude a garment that's worn
primarily or exclusively at night time like pajamas, because normally, especially if
you didn't have electric light, that is not normally a time that
things are seen. Now again, the גמרא Gemara. here emphasizes not the
time of day you're doing the מצוה, mitzvah but the type of
the garment because the assumption is that ציצית are חובת מנא, chovat
mana, are an obligation of the garment, not an obligation of you.
You do not have a מצוה mitzvah, to wear ציצית; if you
have a garment, you have to make sure that there's ציצית on
that garment, on that four-cornered garment. So therefore, if we're going to
exclude things from being visible, we're excluding the type of the garment,
not the time that you're wearing it. So a כסות לילה, ksut
lailah, a night garment like pajamas, are not obligated in ציצית because
those are not normally given for being seen. So the גמרא Gemara.
says, אתה אומר פרט לכסות לילה או אינו אלא פרט לכסות סומא?
ata omer prat leksut lailah o eino ela prat leksut suma? You're
excluding a night-time garment, or maybe it excludes the סומא, suma, the
blind person, but it's exempting garments owned by a סומא, suma, a
blind person, because those are not normally visible to him? כשהוא אומר
אשר תכסה בה הרי כסות סומא אמור. keshehu omer asher techaseh ba
harei ksut suma emur. When it says that you cover yourself with,
which is a more of an inclusive type of a word,
that includes garments of a blind person. המני מקיים וראיתם אותו, hamani
mekayem urisem oso, so what is being excluded from see them? So
it's not people that can't see but it's times you can't see,
פרט לכסות לילה, prat leksut lailah, a night-time garment. ומה ראית לרבות
כסות סומא ולהוציא כסות לילה? uma ra'isa lerabos ksut suma lehotzi ksut
lailah? Why did you divide it this way, include the garments of
a blind person and exclude night-time garments? So, מרבה אני כסות סומא
שישנן בראייה אצל אחרים. marbe ani ksut suma sheyeshnam biriyah etzel acherim.
I would rather include for obligation the garments of a blind person
that other people can see them. So if they're day-time garments worn
by a blind person, they're still in the verse of וראיתם אותו
urisem oso because again, if you focus on the garment, not on
the person, these are visible, they're visible to everybody else in the
world, so it's on a visible garment. ומוציא אני כסות לילה שאינה
בראייה אצל אחרים, umotzi ani ksut lailah sheina biriyah etzel acherim, but
I exclude night-time garments that those are primarily non-visible garments and non-visible
ציצית because they're normally never appear during daytime. So that is what
I learn out.
So אשר תכסה בה asher techaseh ba is coming to include not
other fabrics, but it's coming to include the garments of blind people.
ואימא, veima, says the גמרא, Gemara לרבות שאר בגדים? lerabos shear begadim?
I'm still not convinced, you have אשר תכסה בה, asher techaseh ba,
you would like to use that inclusive phrase to include the garments
of a blind person, I would like to use it to include
other fabrics. Why do you pick the garments of a blind person
over other fabrics? So the גמרא Gemara says מסתברא, mistavra, no, it
makes sense, קאי בצמר ופשתים
מרבה צמר ופשתים. kai betzemer upishtim marbe tzemer upishtim. Since the verse
emphasized wool and linen, so it
says לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדו, lo silbash shaatnez tzemer upishtim
yachdav, and then it says גדילים תעשה לך על ארבע כנפות כסותך
אשר תכסה בה, gidilim taaseh lach al arba kanfos ksutcha asher techaseh
ba,
so... Since it immediately said wool and linen, then when אשר תכסה
בה Asher techaseh bah is being more inclusive, it makes sense to
limit it to wool and linen and include other types of garments
that are still wool and linen garments, garments of a blind person.
So, אטו Atu כאי בצמר ופשתים מרבה שאר בגדים? kai bitzemar u'pishtim
marbe shear begadim? What would it make sense after saying we're talking
about wool and linen to say now we're including other fabrics? If
you said wool and linen, we'll assume we're limiting to wool and
linen and the inclusive is including some other type of a wool
and linen garment. Okay now of course just a minute ago from
ובגד we seemed to do exactly that, start with wool and linen
and end up in other garments, but here we're saying not that
way. So according to this answer, so let's just review. Are other
non-wool and linen garments where the Torah emphasizes wool and linen by
צרעת, tzara'at. by leprosy, whatever the spots, that only those garments are
other fabrics טמא? tamei So according to רבי ישמעאל and רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar it seems to be no, we're
emphasizing wool and linen, but there seems to be maybe. Maybe if
other fabrics are large enough, three טפחים by three טפחים, maybe they
will become טמא. tamei That was certainly רבא'ס Rava's read of רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar it might even be what
רבי ישמעאל winds up saying at the end. So where is it
exclusively wool and linen? Number one, very small sizes, three by three
fingers, or maybe exclusively wool and linen by ציצית. And there, even
though there are inclusive words, we'd rather use them for other things,
but maybe only wool and linen are biblically obligated in ציצית. רבא
says otherwise and this is the debate about how do we rule
practically for ציצית like רבא or not, either way it's obligated rabbinically,
but are these other fabrics obligated biblically? And now we turn back
to,
not turn back, excuse me, we wrap up with another statement of
אביי. Abaye אביי was the one who categorized this by comparing רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon בן אלעזר to רבי שמעון about other fabrics. Let's
take a look now at a similar statement of אביי. אמר אביי:
Amar Abaye: רבי שמעון בן אלעזר וסומכוס אמרו דבר אחד. Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar u'Sumchus amru davar echad. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar and Sumchus
all said the same thing. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר הא דאמרן. Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar ha de'amran. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, what we said,
because now we're going to the other part of רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר. Remember, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר said two statements. One was things
that come from a tree that are not
flax cannot become טמא, tamei. and we interpreted that to mean anything
that's not wool and linen cannot be טמא. tamei And then the
other part of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר'ס Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar's statement
was that things that come from a tree you can use for
סכך sechach except for flax. Flax, because it's a fabric and can
become טמא, tamei you cannot use for סכך. sechach. So now we're
talking about סכך. sechach. So אביי said רבי שמעון בן אלעזר and
סומכוס Sumchus said the same thing about סכך. sechach. רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר הא דאמרן, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar ha de'amran, רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר we quoted yesterday, that you can't use flax for סכך sechach
even if it's not yet woven into a garment. סומכוס דתניא Sumchus
detanya and סומכוס Sumchus we taught in the ברייתא. Beraita, סומכוס אומר,
Sumchus omer, סומכוס Sumchus says, סיככה בטווי פסולה. Sichecha be'tavui pesula.
If you use for סכך sechach a spun thread even though it
is not yet a fabric, that is invalid סכך. sechach. Why? מפני
שמטמאה בנגעים, mipnei she'mitama bene'ga'im,
because it can become טמא tamei for leprosy. Remember נגעים, nega'im remember
we mentioned yesterday that צרעת tzara'at, can make not only fabric טמא,
tamei. but the Torah says בשתי או בערב, bashti o va'erev,
even if it's just the warp and the woof. So therefore, so
therefore
when you say that you cannot use something that can become טמא
tamei for your סכך, sechach, what type of טומאה Tumah are we
talking about?
Every טומאה, Tumah any טומאה? tumah So סומכוס Sumchus says yeah, even
if it's just to become טמא tamei, through צרעת. tzara'at. So you
have here some warp and woof, some spun thread, which is not
a fabric, up on your סוכה succah for your סכך. sechach. No,
sorry, that cannot be good סכך, sechach, it can become טמא. tamei
Not most טומאות, tumot, most טומאות tumot need a fabric. But it
can become טמא Tamei. with צרעת, tzara'at that just requires warp and
woof. And that is similar to the statement of רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר who says that פשתן pishtan linen cannot be used for סכך
sechach and he did not say linen garment, linen fabric, he just
said linen by itself cannot because it can become טמא Tamei through
צרעת. tzara'as, So now the גמרא Gemara ends this up by saying:
כמאן אזלא? Keman azla? Who is this going like? כי האי תנא,
Ki hai tanna, like the following תנא. tanna. דתנן, Detnan, we taught
in the משנה: Mishnah: שתי וערב מיטמאי בנגעים מיד דברי רבי מאיר.
Sheti va'erev mitamei bi'nega'im miyad divrei Rabbi Meir. Warp and woof, those
can become טמא Tamei. with צרעת tzara'as immediately, just the warp and
the woof. Presumably warp and woof, I'll read this like תוספות Tosafot
is specifically referring to wool thread. Wool thread there's a difference between
how you make the warp and the woof, one is longer and
thicker than the other, and it's spun in the counter direction. So
warp and woof immediately, meaning as soon as they're spun, can become
טמא. Tamei. רבי יהודה אומר השתי משישלה. Rabbi Yehuda omer hasheti misheyishaleh.
The שתי, sheti, I forget which is the warp or the woof,
I meant to check it, but one of them,
does anybody see what that is? Danny, you're on the phone there,
do you see what שתי... sheti...
Now okay anyway the השתי shesi as soon as you dry it
outside of the vat. You would put it in a vat for
dyeing it, so that he says because it would normally be dyed,
it would not become טמא Tamei, as soon as it was spun,
it was only considered done and completed after you drew it from
the vat. והערב, veha'erev, however, the other one, מיד. miyad. That is
as soon as it is spun. ואונין של פשתן, ve'unin shel pishtan,
however when it comes to the threads of flax, משיולבנו, misheyilavnu, there
they are considered complete after they are dried and whitened in the
oven. So as opposed to the version that says everything immediately, meaning
or at least the warp and the woof as soon as it
is spun, this opinion says no, different things have different stages where
they are considered to be complete. One where it comes out of
the dyeing vat, the other as soon as it is spun, and
when it comes to flax as soon as it dries in the
oven. So it is not clear exactly who the גמרא Gemara is
linking up, but according to anyway one read of this, the גמרא
Gemara is saying you see that רב יהודה Reb Yehuda explicitly says
we are not just dealing with wool warp and woof, we are
even dealing with פשתן pishtan and linen and even unfinished threads or
even unwoven threads can become טמא, Tamei? and this is consistent with
what we have been teaching. Okay, so that is the issue of
סכך, schach, that because that it can apply to even without a
fabric cannot be used because even warp and woof and thread can
become טמא בנגעים. tamei benega'im. So with that we will end the
previous discussion about all those טומאה tuma issues relating to פשתן. pishtan.
But don't get too excited, we are about to even though we
come to a next משנה, mishnah, we are soon going to revisit
it. So let's start the next משנה. mishnah. משנה. mishnah. כל היוצא
מן העץ אין מדליקין בו אלא פשתן. kol hayotzei min ha'etz ein
madlikin bo ella pishtan. Anything that comes from a tree you cannot
use except for פשתן, pishtan, except for flax. Now what does that
mean? We just heard yesterday that you can use, there was one
opinion that said you could not use certain oils
that come from a tree, only oils that come from fruit, but
that was against the חכמים chachamim and וחכמים vehachachamim say you can
use any oil. And here we are saying no, the only thing
you can use from a tree is flax. So it seems that,
and רש"י Rashi says the difference is are we talking about oils,
not it seems, are we talking about oils or are we talking
about threads. When it comes to oils, there there were some people
who wanted to exclude anything that came from the actual trunk of
the tree. Let's say we reject those. We have a broad category
that includes oils. But now we are not talking about oils, we
are talking about threads. When it comes to threads, you cannot use
threads that are derivative of some type of a tree or bark.
The only thing that you can use that is a thread that
comes from a tree, I not a thread, I mean a wick,
the only type of wick that you can use that comes from
a tree is something that is made out of פשתן, pishtan, out
of linen. Now I will get back to that in a minute
after I read the first line in the גמרא. Gemara, Similarly, וכל
היוצא מן העץ אינו מטמא טומאת אהלים אלא פשתן. vechol hayotzei min
ha'etz eino mitamei tum'at ohalim ella pishtan. Anything that derives from a
tree cannot become טמא Tamei the טומאת אהלים tum'at ohalim of tents
except for linen, פשתן, pishtan, linen and so on. So we will
discuss the טומאה, tuma we will get back to the טומאה tuma
in a second. Let's first read the first line of the גמרא
Gemara about the wicks. מנלן דפשתן איקרי עץ? menalan depishtan ikrei etz?
How do we, what do you mean that anything that comes from
a tree except for פשתן? pishtan? פשתן pishtan I would have called
a plant. Why am I calling it a tree? So אמר מר
זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, how do I know it is called a
tree? דאמר קרא, de'amar kra, the verse says, והיא העלתם הגגה ותטמנם
בפשתי העץ. vahi he'eltam hagaga vatikmenam bepishtei ha'etz. She by רחב Rachav
brought the spies up to the roof
and she hid them with the, with the, you know, the strands
of flax בפשתי העץ. bepishtei ha'etz. So because it says the flax
trees or wood, the wood of the flax, we say that flax
is considered a type of a wood. And therefore, although you cannot
use other types of wood for your wick, you can use פשתן.
pishtan. Now רש"י Rashi says that once we are calling פשתן pishtan
a type of a tree, we are calling all plants a type
of a tree. So what is included in what you cannot use
for wicks? Says רש"י Rashi is cotton, because cotton also grows from
the ground like פשתן pishtan and if we are saying only פשתן
pishtan yes, so cotton no. So תוספות Tosafos goes says goes a
little crazy, I am a little exaggerating, but תוספות Tosafos says if
you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, כל היוצא מן העץ אין
מדליקין, kol hayotzei min ha'etz ein madlikin, פירש קונטרס peresh kuntress כגון
בקנבוס וצמר גפן, kigone bekanvus vetzemer gefen,
like cannabis which might hemp or צמר גפן tzemer gefen or cotton,
because that is like פשתן, pishtan, it is a plant and we
say only פשתן pishtan yes, not others. ואינו נראה לרבינו תם, ve'eino
nireh lerebbeinu Tam, דאם כן יאסר להדליק בו, de'im ken ye'aser lehadlik
bo, you
are telling me I cannot use a cotton wick? והא מעשים בכל
יום שמדליקין בצמר גפן, veha ma'asim bechol yom shemadlikin betzemer gefen, we
know every day we use cotton wicks, וגם טוב מאד לפתילה, vegam
tov me'od lepesilah, that is like ideal wicks are made out of
cotton, so what do you mean we cannot use it? So תוספות
Tosafos says look, really what we are saying is you cannot use
other trees. Things
like what do you call it? Things like cotton are called plants.
They’re not all trees, we’re only excluding tree derivatives. And that’s why
the גמרא Gemara has to say, why am I even calling linen
a tree, flax a tree? I should call flax a plant. So
it says, no, because we have some פסוק that calls flax a
tree. So at the end of the day, all we’re saying is
like this: plants you can definitely use, if they’re good for wicks,
you can use plant derivatives, you go ahead, use cotton, no problem.
Things that come from trees, that you can’t use as wicks. And
by the way, even if you put flax in the tree category
based on this verse, that is something that you can use for
a wick. But they were only—it’s only because we only have to
say it because you might have put flax into the tree category.
The real answer is that anything that is a plant is fine,
what’s being excluded are trees. Okay, so that’s as far as the
flax is concerned. Now we continue,
now we continue, so with what do you call it, with going
back to טומאה וטהרה. Tumah v’Taharah Now we really have a little
bit of time, if people are okay, I would say let’s try
to get a little bit ahead, okay, at least get through this
טומאה tuma וטהרה stuff, so we’re going to go until 9:30 today,
do the full hour. So let’s take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara היוצא מן העץ אינו מטמא טומאת אהלים אלא פשתן. Hayotzei min
ha’etz eino metamei tumat ohalim ela pishtan. And the only thing that
comes from a tree that again, putting flax for whatever reason in
that category, that causes טומאה tuma. of tents is flax, linen. Now
what does this mean? If there’s a dead body under a roof,
everything under the roof becomes טמא. Tamei. It doesn’t really matter what
that roof is made of, it doesn’t matter if that roof is
fixed, it doesn’t matter if it’s attached to the ground, it doesn’t
matter if it’s just being suspended momentarily, although there is a discussion
about אהל זרוק, Ohel Zaruk, but whatever, anything under a one-by-one טפח
Tefach type of a roof becomes טמא Tamei if there’s a dead
body. There’s another טומאה tuma, which we’re referring to here, which is
טומאת אהלים, Tumat Ohalim, which means that the roof itself becomes טמא.
Tamei. It says והזה על האהל ועל כל הכלים, V’hizah al ha’ohel
v’al kol hakelim, you sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah on the tent itself, even the tent becomes טמא. Tamei. Now
if this is a מטלטלין Metaltelin chattel, not attached to the ground,
okay, if you’ve got a, I don’t know, a board being suspended
over a dead body, so actually that’s פשוטי כלי עץ, Pshutei Klei
Etz, but whatever it is, if you’ve got a salad bowl being
suspended over a dead body, so it both serves as a roof
to bring טומאה tuma to things underneath it and the salad bowl
becomes טמא, Tamei. it’s directly over the dead body. But let’s say
it’s not a salad bowl, let’s say you have a dead body
in your house, so does your house itself become טמא? Tamei Does
it remain—do the walls and the roof remain טמא Tamei, and if
I touch the roof even after the dead body is removed? So
the obvious answer is no, something that’s מחובר לקרקע, Mechubar l’karka, that’s
attached to the ground, does not become טמא. Tamei, However, there is
something that will become טמא tamei even if it is attached to
the ground. And that is if you have a type of a
material, let’s say you make a tent, so let’s say you make
a tent out of wool, a wool tent, and there you have
a dead body in the tent, so you know what, even if
the tent is pitched, the wool tent will become טמא. tamei. Now
let’s say it’s made out of linen, the linen tent will become
טמא. tamei. Let’s say it’s made out of leather, we’ll find out
in a minute that leather becomes טמא. tamei Okay, these things do
become טמא tamei, if they’re fabric types of materials. So if it’s
attached to the ground and it’s a building material, wood or metal
or whatever, not a problem. But if it is attached to the
ground and a fabric type of a material or a clothing material,
then it can become טמא, tamei, טומאת אהלים. Tumat Ohalim. And here
we are saying is the only thing that is a wood derivative
that falls into this category is linen. So if you’ve got some
other type of a fabric made from, I don’t know, tree bark
strings or something, and certainly if you just have actual planks of
wood, then if it’s attached to the ground, it will not be
טמא, tamei. but if it’s linen, it will, if there’s a dead
body under it, this is טומאת אהלים. Tumat Ohalim. So let’s take
a look about this in the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: מנלן אמר רבי אליעזר גמר אהל אהל ממשכן. Minalan
amar Rabbi Eliezer gamar ohel ohel miMishkan.
So that was—so we learn out גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah from the
משכן. Mishkan. כתיב הכא זאת התורה אדם כי ימות באהל, K’tiv hacha
zot haTorah adam ki yamut b’ohel, it says here,
this is the law if a person dies in a tent. וכתיב
התם ויפרוש את האהל על המשכן, U’ktiv hatam vayifros et ha’ohel al
haMishkan, it says there, he spread
the אהל Ohel over the משכן. Mishkan. מה להלן של פשתן קרוי
אהל, Mah l’halan shel pishtan karui ohel, we know there that one
of the coverings of the משכן, Mishkan, the lowest one, which is
sometimes called the משכן Mishkan itself,
included
linen because it says שש משזר Shesh moshzar and שש Shesh is
linen. So therefore, the same way that was made out of flax
and is called an אהל, Ohel, is made out of linen. אף
כאן של פשתן קרוי אוהל af kan shel pishtan karui ohel here
too it's only something of linen is called an אוהל. ohel. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if you want to learn from
there: אי מה להלן שזורין וחוטין כפול ו' אף כאן שזורין וחוטין
כפול ו'. ee ma lehalan shezurin vechutin kaful vav af kan shezurin
vechutin kaful vav. There it's only if the strings are sort of
spun and wrapped around, like there are six-fold strings. We learn that
from the word שש. shesh. שש shesh means not only linen, but
it also means six. So the strings are twisted into into groups
of six. So אף כאן שזורין וחוטין כפול ו', af kan shezurin
vechutin kaful vav, would you say that only the type of a
linen tent that becomes טמא tamei, is something that is of a
similar configuration? תלמוד לומר אוהל אוהל ריבה. talmud lomar ohel ohel riba.
No, it says אוהל ohel more than once to be more broad,
to include even without that. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי אוהל
אוהל ריבה, ee ohel ohel riba, if we're being inclusive, אפילו כל
מילי נמי, afilu kol mili nami, then you shouldn't limit yourself to
linen, you should say all types of fabrics become טמא. tamei, So
the גמרא Gemara says no: אם כן גזירה שוה מאי אהני ליה?
im ken gezeira shava mai ahanei leh? Then why would the גזירה
שוה gezeira shava link it to linen? So on the one hand
it's linked to linen, on the other hand it's inclusive, so it
includes all configurations of linen, but still only linen, not other things.
Now again, it's interesting what not other things means. Not other things
does not mean not other fabrics. If it's a wool tent, it's
also טמא. tamei. Not other things means not other wood derivatives. So
it's a pretty funny way of excluding. We first put linen in
the wood category and then we say we're including linen but we're
excluding other wood derivatives. But other things maybe yes, like I said,
wool would be included. Okay. And partly we're going to learn other
things, so other things are also the אוהל ohel of the משכן,
mishkan, are fabrics used in the משכן. mishkan. Okay, so let's come,
you know, in the actual curtains or whatever the fabrics on the
top of the משכן. mishkan. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר קרא ואימא מה להלן קרשים אף כאן קרשים. amar kra
ve'eima ma lehalan krashim af kan krashim. Why don't I say, the
same way
there it's only a linen tent which is built upon wood beams,
so maybe the only type of linen tent that becomes טמא tamei.
is if the walls are made out of wood beams like you
had in the משכן? mishkan? אמר קרא—no, amar kra the verse says:
ועשית קרשים למשכן. ve'asita krashim lamishkan. You should make the beams for
the
משכן. mishkan. משכן קרוי משכן ואין קרשים קרויין משכן. mishkan karui mishkan
ve'ein krashim kruyin mishkan. The משכן mishkan is called the משכן. mishkan.
The actual fabric on the top is what's called the משכן. mishkan.
The beams are not the משכן; mishkan; the beams are supporting the
משכן. mishkan. So since משכן mishkan is called an אוהל, ohel, and
אוהל ohel is what becomes טמא, tamei.
so it is the fabric that becomes טמא, tamei and you do
not need the beams to make the fabric considered a tent. The
fabric on its own is what is called the tent; the beams
are considered for the tent, for the משכן, mishkan, but they are
not the tent itself. And therefore, even without beams, it will become
טמא. tamei רש"י, Rashi, by the way, says the question is maybe
the beams themselves should be טמא, tamei but תוספות Tosafot says, I
think, it's the simpler read of the גמרא, Gemara that maybe you
need beams in order for the fabric to be טמא, tamei. and
the גמרא Gemara says no, they are not the actual משכן mishkan
itself. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, now that
you're saying that, ועשית מכסה לאוהל, ve'asita michseh laohel, הכי נמי מכסה
לא איקרי אוהל. hachi nami michseh lo ikri ohel. So if that's
true, that the beams for the משכן mishkan are not the beams—are
not the משכן, mishkan, so it says you should make a covering
for the אוהל. ohel. What's the covering for the אוהל? ohel? עורות
אילים מאדמים ועורות תחשים, orot eilim me'odamim ve'orot techashim, right, red-dyed rams'
skins and the skin of a תחש. tachash. So we're going to
discuss what a תחש tachash is. So there it says that will
be a covering for the משכן, mishkan, but they themselves are not
considered the משכן, mishkan, which means that they themselves are not considered
an אוהל, ohel, which would mean that an אוהל ohel made out
of leather, right, which is what this was, would not become טמא.
tamei So the גמרא Gemara says:
אלא מעתה הכי נמי מכסה לא איקרי אוהל—the ela me'ata hachi nami
michseh lo ikri ohel covering itself is not the אוהל, ohel, it's
a covering for the אוהל, ohel, this leather covering. So
if that's true, אלא הא דבעי רבי אלעזר—רבי אלעזר: עור בהמה טמאה
מהו שיטמא באוהל המת? or behema t'meiah mahu she'yitama be'ohel hamet? Let's
say you have the leather of a non-kosher animal, will that have
the טומאת אוהל? tumat ohel? If you have the roof of a
tent, let's say, made out of leather of a non-kosher animal, will
that become the טומאה tumah of tents? Why is he asking? השתא
עור בהמה טהורה לא
מטמא—you hashta or behema tehorah lo mitama know, if the leather covering
of the משכן mishkan is not considered the משכן, mishkan, not the
אוהל, ohel, then I don't know that any leather can become טמא.
tamei Even the leather of a kosher animal I have no basis
for saying it's טמא. tamei. עור בהמה טמאה מיבעיא? or behema t'meiah
miba'aya? Why is he asking the leather of a non-kosher animal? The
fact that he's asking the leather of a non-kosher animal makes it
clear that we're taking for granted that the leather of a kosher
animal is part
of So the
גמרא Gemara says no, שני התם דהדר הדר קרא. shani hatam dehadar
hadar kera.
There it's different because the verse goes back and includes the leather
covering as part of the tent itself. דכתיב, Dechtiv, it says ונשאו
את יריעת המשכן, venasu et yeriat hamishkan, they shall carry the like
curtains for the משכן, mishkan, ואת אהל מועד, ve-et ohel moed, the
tent the אהל מועד ohel moed itself, מכסהו, michsehu, its covering, ומכסה
התחש אשר עליו מלמעלה, umichse hatachash asher alav milmalah,
and the covering of the תחש, tachash, right, there was the covering
first of the red of the red
dyed ram skin and then there was the skin of the תחש.
tachash. So those are the coverings of the אהל מועד. ohel moed.
So מקיש עליון לתחתון, makish elyon letachton, it links the upper to
the lower. מה תחתון קרוי אהל, ma tachton karuy ohel, the same
way the bottom thing is the אהל מועד, ohel moed, אף עליון
קרוי אהל. af elyon karuy ohel. So since it wraps them all
together אהל מועד מכסהו ומכסה התחש, ohel moed michsehu umichse hatachash, somehow
that big sort of listing them together says they're all part of
the אהל. ohel. So the beams are not part of the אהל,
ohel, but the various coverings are and therefore I know that one
of those coverings is made out of leather and therefore I know
that leather has טומאת אהלים. tumat ohalim. So what do I know?
This idea that the tent itself becomes טמא tamei, even attached to
the ground is learned by connection to the אהל מועד ohel moed
the משכן, mishkan, and there I have number one a fabric made
out of linen, I have fabrics made out of wool, I have
the covering on top of the first level, you know there's a
second level made out of goat's hair, so that's a second level
of, so I know that that comes that that type of a
fabric also, and I know that leather, all those types of fabrics
can become טומאת אהלים. tumat ohalim. And the question is what about
leather of non-kosher animals? Okay, but certainly linen is included but other
what do you call it other wood derivatives not. So let's take
a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. One minute. Right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. גופא, Gufa, let's go back now and
look at that question about leather of non-kosher animals. בעי רבי אלעזר,
Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar, Rabbi Elazar asked, Rabbi Elazar I should say, עור
בהמה טמאה מהו שיטמא טומאת אהלים? or behemah temeah mahu she-yitame tumat
ohalim? What is the story of the leather of non-kosher animals? Is
that included in a type of a fabric of tents that can
become טמא tamei itself? So מאי קמיבעיא ליה, mai kamibaia leh, what
is the question about? Meaning what's at the root of the question?
So אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda Bar Ahava, תחש
שהיה בימי משה קמיבעיא ליה. tachash shehayah bimei Moshe kamibaia leh. This
תחש tachash where it says that that was in addition to the
leather of the ram, the red dyed leather of the ram, it
says the leather of a תחש. tachash. So he wants to know
what type of an animal this תחש tachash was. So was it
a kosher animal non-kosher? If it was kosher, we have no basis
for including non-kosher skins of non-kosher animals. But maybe the תחש tachash
was a non-kosher animal. So קמיבעיא ליה, kamibaia leh, טמא היה או
טהור היה, tame hayah o tahor hayah, was it a kosher or
non-kosher animal? So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, מאי תיבעי ליה,
mai tiba'i leh, what type of question is that? תנינא, Tanina, we
taught in a ברייתא, Beraita לא הוכשרו למלאכת שמים אלא עור בהמה
טהורה בלבד. lo huchsheru limlechet shamayim ella or behemah tehorah bilvad. The
only thing you can use for heavenly purposes, which presumably it's a
funny phrase מלאכת שמים, melechet shamayim, not מצוה, מלאכת שמים, melechet shamayim,
is kosher skins of kosher animals. So presumably that means building of
the משכן mishkan that you only use skins of kosher animals. So
not, so that answers your question. So גמרא Gemara says מתיב רבי
אבא, Metiv Rabbi Abba, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, I'll ask
you on this. רבי יהודה אומר, שני מכסאות היו. Rabbi Yehuda omer
shenei michsaot hayu, You want to say that it had to be
a kosher animal, but wait, we have a ברייתא braisa, that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says there were two coverings, right? When it says
the covering of the ram skin and the covering of the תחש,
tachash, were those two coverings or one covering? So this is a
debate. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer, שני מכסאות היו, shenei michsaot
hayu. there were two coverings. אחד של עורות אילים מאדמים, Echad shel
orot eilim me-odamim, one of the red dyed ram skins, ואחד של
עורות תחשים, ve-echad shel orot tchasheem, and one of the תחש tachash
skins. Because that's you know the פסוק says this covering and that
covering. רבי נחמיה אומר, Rabbi Nechemiah omer, מכסה אחד היה. michseh echad
hayah. No, it was a combined hybrid covering, ודומה כמין טלא אילן.
ve-domeh kemin tala ilan. If you look you know they have that
nice book, the משכן, Mishkan, where they have a nice way where
they have a nice sort of a way they imagine it, like
a sort of a V-cut where part the outside of the V
is I think the ram skin and the inside is this תחש
tachash skin. Whatever it was, it was some type of a skin
of a covering of leather that was the combined two leathers. Okay,
ודומה, ve-domeh, now we're going to talk about what this תחש tachash
was, ודומה כמין טלא אילן. ve-domeh kemin tala ilan. It's like a
טלא אילן, tala ilan, which is some non-kosher animal. Again, Soncino has
some suggestions what that was, I think he has some type of
a cat-like animal that has a spotted tail or something. Whatever it
is. So the גמרא says והא טלא אילן טמא הוא? Ve-ha tala
ilan tame hu? But that טלא אילן tala ilan is a non-kosher
animal. So you see we're assuming that the תחש tachash could be
non-kosher. So that's really not a question. גמרא says no, הכי קאמר,
hachi ka'amar, כמין טלא אילן, kemin tala ilan, it looked like a
like a טלא אילן, Tala Ilon, who שיש בו גוונים הרבה, she-yeish
bo gevanim harbei, it's multi-colored. Whatever this תחש Tachash is, it's multi-colored.
So טלא אילן Tala Ilon was the
comparison, ולא טלא אילן, v'lo Tala Ilon, it itself is not a
טלא אילן, Tala Ilon, דאילו התם טמא, d'ilu hasam tamei, that's a
non-kosher animal, והכא טהור, v'hacha tahor, we can argue that the תחש
Tachash itself is טהור. tahor. It's only the טלא אילן Tala Ilon
that is no good, that's used as a comparison. Okay, so we
still don't know what this תחש Tachash was and whether it was
kosher or non-kosher. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, אי הכי, i hachi, היינו דמתרגמינן, hainu d'metargminan, ah, you're
telling me it's multi-colored, now I get the תרגום, Targum, now I
get the Aramaic translation, right they had a standard Aramaic translation, we
assume it's אונקלוס, Onkelos, it might have been a variation not exactly
our אונקלוס, Onkelos, but whatever, they had a standard Aramaic translation of
the תורה. Now that you told me the תחש Tachash is multi-colored,
I get the translation because what did the translation say? היינו דמתרגמינן
ססגונא, hainu d'metargminan Sasgona, that the translation of תחש Tachash is ססגונא.
Sasgona. What is ססגונא? Sasgona? So here's what it means: ששש בגוונים
הרבה, she-sas bi-gevanim harbei, it rejoices in its many colors. So ססגונא
Sasgona is a way of referring to some multi-colored animal and that's
what the תחש Tachash is. I should say that there are two
major suggestions about what this תחש Tachash is. Some people want to
say it's a narwhal, which is some type of an obviously of
a marine animal, and apparently when you take it out of water
its skin does have some colors. I don't know exactly how they
got it out of the ocean,
maybe it washed up after the splitting of the ים סוף Yam
Suf on the banks there. And the other possibility is that Felix,
who wrote the book on the flora and fauna of the תורה,
he suggests that it's a giraffe, which actually is nice, that certainly
gives you multi-colors right over there. Okay, so anyway we will see
another feature which makes people identify, try to identify it with those
two animals. Now a giraffe by the way is kosher. So this
is the question: kosher or non-kosher. רבא אמר, Rava amar, עור בהמה
טמאה דמטמאי באהל המת מהכא. or behema tmeia d'metamei b'ohel hameis mehacha.
Here's where we get it from, not from arguing that the תחש
Tachash was a non-kosher animal, we get the idea that leather of
non-kosher animals causes טומאת מת tumas meis from the following. דתניא, Detanya,
we learned in the ברייתא, עור. or. It says leather. When it's
talking about a טומאת מת. tumas meis. או בעור, O ba'or, or
leather, again that extra או o tells me ריבה, ribba, to be
more inclusive.
עור בהמה טמאה. Or behema tmeia. I'm sorry, this is not טומאת
מת, tumas meis, excuse me. This is talking about by צרעת, tzara'as?
by נגעים again. So it says if it appears on leather, או
בעור, o ba'or, leather, comes to tell me even the leather of
a non-kosher animal. And it tells me another thing, ושלאקה בביאת כהן.
v'she'lakah b'bi'as kohen. The verse says something has צרעת tzara'as. and you
bring it to the כהן. kohen. Let's say you showed it to
the כהן kohen and as you're showing it that's when the spot
appeared or the טמא tamei. spot appeared. It's like the opposite of
when you bring your car to the mechanic, right? You bring your
car to the mechanic and the funny noise goes away. Here you
thought there was a problem, you brought it to the כהן, kohen,
when the כהן kohen started looking at it it was fine, but
then as he continued to look at it the spot grew or
something and it became a problem. So maybe that's not טמא. tamei,
So the או o tells you yes that is טמא tamei, as
well.
וקצץ מכולן ועשה אחת מהן מנין? Uketzatz m'kulan v'asah achas mehen, minayin?
Now how about if I cut, if I took different fabrics, a
little leather, a little wool, a little linen, and I made a
whole little patchwork. How do I know that something made of a
hybrid of fabrics can become טמא tamei from צרעת? tzara'as, So תלמוד
לומר, talmud lomar, the verse teaches, או בכל מלאכת עור. o be'chol
meleches or. Another עור. or. עור Or in any type of thing
created out of leather. So even some hybrid fabric can also become
טמא. tamei, Anyway, all of that is learned by צרעת. tzara'as And
one of the things we learn is leather of a non-kosher animal.
So therefore from there I'm somehow going to apply it to the
טומאה tumah of tents. ואיכא, Ve'ika, so the גמרא says, one minute,
איכא למיפרך, i-ka l'mifrach, you can challenge that. How can you apply
it to the טומאה tumah of tents? מה לנגעים שכן שתי וערב
טמא בהן? Mah l'nega'im she-kein sh'si va'erev tamei bahen? Maybe it's only
by צרעת, tzara'as צרעת tzara'at. has that special feature that warp and
woof become טמא, tamei it's not true even by dead bodies. So
you can't apply the טומאה tumah of צרעת tzara'at the materials to
tent. So the גמרא says, אלא גמר משרצים. ella gamar mishratzim. Fine,
I'll learn it from טומאה of dead שרצים, shratzim, which is a
more generic טומאה. דתניא, Detanya, עור, or, because there it says by
if a dead rodent touches leather. אין לי אלא עור בהמה טהורה.
ein li ela or behema tehora. Again, maybe it would only be
leather of kosher animals. עור בהמה טמאה מנין? Or behema tmeia minayin?
How do I know leather of non-kosher animals? תלמוד לומר או עור.
Talmud lomar o or. Again, או o or leather. So once I
know it's true by שרצים, shratzim, that's a very low level generic
טומאה, certainly it would be true by the טומאה of dead bodies
and tents. But the גמרא still says, one minute, maybe not. ואיכא
למיפרך, ve'ika l'mifrach, you can challenge this.
מה לשרצים שכן מטמאי בכעדשה? mah lishratzim she-kein metamei b'ch'adasha? שרצים, Shratzim,
even a size of a lentil bean becomes טמא tamei. if it's
a dead rodent. A dead body you need a כזית k'zayis which
is a A larger size. So the גמרא says, okay, נגעים יוכיחו,
nega'im yokhichu, but I'll prove it against that from spots of צרעת.
tzara'at That's even not a lentil size. That's the size of a
larger size. That's the size of a גריס, gris, of like a
different type of a bean. So the גמרא says, a larger size.
וחזר הדין, vechazar hadin, and you go back and forth between these
two examples of צרעת tzara'at and dead rodents. Each one other type
of leathers become טמא. tamei לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי
זה כראי זה, lo re'i zeh kire'i zeh velo re'i zeh kire'i
zeh, each one's distinguishing characteristics are not like the other. הצד השווה
שבהן, hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator is שעור טמא בהן, she'or
tamei bahen, that number one, leather can become טמא, tamei and number
two, ועשה עור בהמה טמאה כעור בהמה טהורה, ve'asah or beheimah teme'ah
ke'or beheimah tehorah, there's no distinction between leather of kosher animals and
non-kosher animals. אף אני אביא אהל המת, af ani avi ohel hamet,
I will therefore include the tent over dead bodies, שעור טמא בו,
she'or tamei bo, number one, I already know, I'm not going to
make up the idea that leather becomes טמא, tamei the Torah is
already explicit that leather becomes טמא of tents over dead bodies. But
once I know leather becomes טמא, ונעשה בו עור בהמה טמאה כעור
בהמה טהורה, vena'aseh bo or beheimah teme'ah ke'or beheimah tehorah, leather doesn't
matter, kosher or non-kosher animals. Okay. So now we've raised the question:
we know flax, we know wool, we know goat, we know leather.
How about leather of non-kosher animals, does that become טמא when it's
a tent over dead body? So one way of discussing this is
whether it's a תחש, tachash, which the משכן Mishkan was made out
of was טמא. Another way of saying it is maybe we learn
it out from these other categories, from this category of צרעת tzara'at.
and שרצים, shratzim, even leather of non-kosher animals. So אמר ליה רבא
מברניש לרב אשי, amar leh Rava mibarnish leRav Ashi, so if we
can learn it out, what was the question that was raised, what
was רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer question? Here we can learn it
out from these other categories. So he said, look, here's the problem.
איכא למיפרך, ika lemifrach, you can challenge that. מה להצד השווה שבהן,
mah lehatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator, שכן מטמאים בפחות מכזית. sheken
mitamm'im bepachot mikezayit. Whether it's צרעת Tzara'at or whether it's a שרץ,
sheretz, each one is still less than a כזית. kezayit. Either it
goes by the side of an עדשה, adashah, one type of a
bean, or a גריס, gris, a different type of a bean, but
they're less than a כזית. kezayit. So maybe they're considered more strict,
at least in one way, and just because leather of non-kosher animals
there is טמא does not mean it's true by dead bodies. תאמר
במת שאינו מטמא אלא בכזית, tomar bemet she'eino metamei ella bekezayit, you
can't necessarily apply it to a dead body that requires a
כזית. kezayit. אלא אמר רבא מברניש, ella amar Rava mibarnish, so that's
not what we're going to learn it out from. Top of כח
עמוד ב. kaf chet amud bet. אתיא בקל
וחומר מנוצה של עזים. atya bekal vachomer minotzah shel izim. We'll make
it a קל וחומר kal vachomer, from the down of goats. שאין
מטמא בנגעים, she'ein metamei benega'im, that's not mentioned anywhere by צרעת. tzara'at,
צרעת tzara'at, does not include goats' hair. ומטמא באהל המת, umetamei be'ohel
hamet, but it is by dead body, but it is by אהל
המת. ohel hamet. How do I know it's by an אהל המת?
ohel hamet? Because I know that the משכן Mishkan is made from
the משכן Mishkan which is the paradigm for the אהל המת—it's ohel
hamet pretty funny that the
משכן Mishkan where God's presence is the paradigm for אהל המת, ohel
hamet, but okay—if that משכן, Mishkan, one of the coverings of the
drapes, of the curtains above, was made out of goats, goats' hair.
So goats' hair, I know it's a more inclusive category. Goats' hair
normally is not a fabric, it doesn't work for צרעת, tzara'at and
nevertheless it works for this טומאה of tents. So that's true, so
it's a קל וחומר then to leather of non-kosher animals.
שאין מטמא בנגעים ומטמא באהל המת, she'ein metamei benega'im umetamei be'ohel hamet,
עור בהמה טמאה שמטמא בנגעים, or beheimah teme'ah shemetamei benega'im, leather of
non-kosher animals that is טמא by צרעת, אינו דין שמטמא באהל המת?
eino din shemetamei be'ohel hamet? It certainly could become טמא in with
a tent. So now we have basically concluded either by learning it
from צרעת by some הצד השווה hatzad hashaveh or a קל וחומר,
we have learned that the טומאה of tents includes all leathers, even
leathers of non-kosher animals. So now the גמרא says, if that's true,
אלא דל הא דתני רב יוסף, ella dal ha detani Rav Yosef,
לא הוכשרו במלאכת שמים אלא בעור בהמה טהורה בלבד, lo huchsharu bimlechet
shamayim ella be'or beheimah tehorah bilvad, if we're saying the only thing
you could use for heavenly purposes is leather of kosher animals, now
you're telling me that that might
mean the משכן. Mishkan. It's possible the תחש tachash was a non-kosher
animal. So if that's true, meaning we don't know either way but
it's possible, למאי הלכתא, lemai hilcheta, why is he coming to tell
me? So למאי הלכתא, lemai hilcheta, why's he telling me? And even
if he wants to argue that the תחש tachash was a kosher
animal, but that's historical, that has no practical relevance. Once we're saying
the הלכה halachah is that the טומאה of tents applies to non-kosher
leather, why is he bothering telling me this idea? What's a practical
application of the idea that you can only use kosher leathers? Maybe
it's true about the משכן, Mishkan, maybe not, but that's not practical
for us. What's a practical application? So the גמרא says,
למאי הלכתא, lemai hilcheta, what's the practical application? So the גמרא says,
לתפילין, letfillin, to tell me what you can make תפילין tefillin out
of. Out of that maybe you can only make תפילין tefillin out
of כשר kosher leather, leather from כשר kosher animals. So we will
pick up with this tomorrow about number one what are we saying
how it has to be made out of leather of כשר kosher
animals? It's not applying, we don't know about the משכן Mishkan historically,
certainly is not limiting the הלכה halacha of the טומאה of tents.
What is the purpose of saying leather of כשר kosher animals? And
we're also for those that wanted were still interested in the תחש
tachash going to circle back to the תחש tachash and discuss what
type of an animal that might have been. So we will pick
up with that tomorrow. Okay everybody should keep dry and safe. Be
well. כל טוב. kol tuv. Bye.